If you listen closely,
you can hear it. The scream of your
liver.
Okay, maybe not literally, but if a
massive impressive new study has
anything to say, it's going to be
exactly that with probably a few more
complex words thrown in. In this study,
which was published in the gargantuan
journal Cell, scientists have discovered
how our diet marches our healthy liver
down the path of cancer, ultimately
turning our liver cancerous. Before we
get into how your liver balloons, how it
strikes and leaves its job being the
liver, and how the loss of its ability
to generate ketones relates to its slide
towards cancer, we should probably zoom
out and look at the evidence that isn't
mechanistic, meaning evidence that
speaks to the everyday person. So, we
can look at a huge study, including tens
of thousands of people, and ask a simple
question. Does a bad diet raise our risk
of liver cancer? Well, the answer is
yes. We'll get into what bad diet means
later, but for now, just know that a bad
diet, which you can probably imagine a
few examples off the top of your head,
is linked to increased risk of liver
cancer. Now, I'd like to take you down
this rabbit hole, which includes images
of livers bubbling and ballooning like
eggs on a frying pan. Liver cells
turning away from being liver cells and
this mysterious loss of a ketogenic
potential by the liver. I'll explain
what I mean. So, as we shift to the
primary study, we're looking at data in
mice and some in humans as well. In said
study, they show that one of the first
visual signs of the liver figuratively
screaming is the ballooning that can
occur when the liver is injured from
repeatedly consuming a poor diet. We see
images here. The white sections are
raised almost like a bubble forming
within the structure of the liver. This
is a sign of what's known as massled
metabolic dysfunctional association
steotic liver disease. So harm occurs to
the liver over years and then the liver
cells say, "Okay, I've had enough. I've
had enough of this." And that shows
itself here. The top image is when a
normal healthy diet is fed. And the
bottom image is the unhealthy diet. The
pinkish purple there is a fluorescent
marker of the border of the cells. And
the zoomed in images allow you to see
the kind of cyan looking color. That's a
marker of if the cell is well still a
liver cell. Notice how the bottom
condition, the blue, the cyan, whatever,
is missing in multiple cells. That tells
us that the poor nutrition is leading to
something called differentiation.
Essentially, the liver cells are turning
away from being liver cells and turning
into well, how do I put this? Uh, a
nondescript blob. They're essentially
saying, "We're open for work because
we're no longer liver cells." So, up to
now, poor diet leads to serious liver
stress, which causes the liver to deform
and liver cells to begin reverting back
to a more naive non-liver origin. Now,
you may or may not know this, but your
body has the ability to convert fat
molecules into essentially
pre-tabolized, pre-prepared fat
molecules called ketones. And if you've
ever heard of ketosis, which is achieved
through longerterm fasting or very low
carbohydrate diets like a ketogenic
diet, ketones are produced by your
liver. So obviously, if the liver cells
are no longer liver cells, you can
imagine that they aren't producing
ketones anymore, which means that they
are no longer going to produce ketone
enzymes. One of the chief ketone enzymes
is HMGCS2.
So what we can then do in humans is
track the downfall of HMGCS2
as a marker of this massiffiation
of the liver cells. So that's what
happens when we track the amount of this
enzyme in human livers and compare
between the healthy liver and a
cancerous one. The cancerous one has
marketkedly reduced levels of this
ketone enzyme. And even between cancers,
when we get tissue of liver cancer in
people, there's worse survival of people
with liver cancer if they have reduced
liver production of this ketone enzyme.
So several lines of evidence are
pointing to the fact that the liver
cancer is associated with lower
expression of these ketone enzymes and
likely reduced ketosis potential. But we
don't actually know that yet because
these are still associations. However,
we can understand the relationship this
all has to ketosis by simply
artificially removing the enzyme and
seeing what happens to cancer. So, for
this, we turn back to animal models to
bridge the gap between association and
causation by literally cutting out the
ketone enzyme gene from the liver cells.
So, they can't produce the enzyme and
therefore ketones even if they wanted
to. So, when comparing those livers that
couldn't produce ketones to those that
could across a series of different pro
and anti-cancerous genes, there were
some fascinating discoveries. One, a
crap diet pushes our gene expression
toward a cancerous one, regardless of
the situation. But two, if you knock out
the ketone production, that push towards
a cancerous gene expression is even
stronger. the slow march toward cancer
becomes more so a sprint. This was
further evidenced when looking at cancer
tumor size. Both conditions are fed a
crap diet, but the knockout of the
ketone producing enzyme leads to greater
tumor growth. In the end, what we're
learning here is that yes, your poor
diet is pressuring your liver to turn
cancerous. However, ketones are likely
acting as a pressure relief valve,
reducing the procancerous pressure. How
incredible is that? Now, if you haven't
been following the physionic journey
closely, you may have missed this video
that I released last year, which was on
a different study making an argument for
ketone production by the liver being a
release valve of pressure, protecting
the liver from becoming diseased in the
first place. I'll link in the in the
description. So, this is not
unprecedented. However, this is the
first study that I'm aware of to really
describe the march towards cancer. Okay,
so how should we think about all this?
Now, I'll put this really simply for
you, but if you're looking for a deeper
dive, like understanding the use of gene
signatures to identify liver cancer
progression in the research, a more
detailed analysis of the specific foods
that are protective, and more, then
check out the insider version of this
analysis that you're currently watching.
It comes with an article, you get a
private podcast, access to my
selfdesigned AI, live sessions with me,
and more. The way to access is to join
the Physionic Insiders research
platform. It's linked in the description
box. I hope to speak with you over
there. Now, it's pretty simple really. A
crap diet is probably what you already
know is a crap diet. I mean, in what
world is McDonald's or Burger King and
so on been on the health food list? But
to get more granular with it, here's how
to stuff a sock in your liver's scream
towards cancer. Or if you want to be a
bit kinder than a soft stroke on its
head, saying, "Sh,
shh, it's okay. It's okay, little
hippado. It's okay."
Generally, avoiding added sugars, trans
fats, and alcohol are big ones. Anything
that leads to a fattier liver, gaining
too much general body fat, as an
example, or eating an abundance of
ultrarocessed foods, focusing on whole
foods, that's an excellent way to shift
towards an anti-cancerous liver profile.
Again, it's the obvious things. I'm sure
there are some more direct targets like
drugs and supplements, but the biggest
movers are going back to the basics in
this case. And remember how I mentioned
that ketones act as a release valve? I
make a preliminary argument for how
ketosispromoting habits like ketogenic
diets and fasting could be especially
protective. I cover that in this next
video. Check it out. I hope you found
this as fascinating as I did. Thanks for
tuning in and I'll catch you in the next
one. See you.